MISSION 56 "IT'S JUST… CHRISTMAS."
（任务56 圣诞快乐）
December 24. Christmas Eve.
12月24日 圣诞夜
Komi has no plans.
古见同学没有安排任何计划
RING
（铃声）
Hello, Komi?
喂？古见同学
Christmas party at your house on the 24th! Buy a present to exchange!
我们24号要在你家办圣诞派对 你要买好交换礼物喔
The budget is 2,000 yen. Bye!
预算是2000日元 再见！
FREEZE
（静止）
Komi realized she's not confident choosing a present by herself.
古见同学发现没有独自挑礼物的自信
What would people be happy to receive?
她在烦恼要买什么礼物大家才会开心
Going alone to the station…
而且还要独自前往车站商场
Will she be able to go shopping without a major incident?
她能顺利买到东西吗？
LITTLE BROTHER (SHOSUKE) JUST HAPPENED BY
（碰巧经过的弟弟 笑介）
SHE FORCED HIM TO COME ALONG
（古见同学强迫他一起来）
RUMBLE
（隆隆声）
NEKOYA
（猫咪屋）
GLIDES
（跑）
-THIS WILL DO. -1KG OF BROKEN RICE CRACKERS
（就挑这个吧 混装一公斤碎仙贝）
WANTS TO LEAVE
（想回家）
-The little brother wants to leave. -SHUFFLE
-她的弟弟想回家 -（快步走）
"I'll narrow it down to three," says the big sister.
姐姐表示“我会选三个再请你挑”
And then Komi's present options, number one.
于是古见同学找到礼物候选一号
-A selection of candles. -CANDLES
-混装蜡烛包 -（蜡烛）
NOD
（点头）
Number two.
第二号
-A reindeer motif vase. -VASE
-麋鹿的花瓶 -（花瓶）
SMUG
（沾沾自喜）
Number three.
第三号…
HO HO HO
（大笑）
A dancing Santa doll.
会跳舞的圣诞老人娃娃
He didn't like any of them.
笑介认为那都是一堆废物
SHUFFLE
（快步走）
Let's go to the toy store next! Toys!
我们接下来去玩具店吧！
Yes, dear.
知道了
HMMMMM
（烦恼）
And then…
然后…
TA-DA!
（看吧）
-BUY IT FOR ME! -POINT
（帮我付钱 用手指示）
SHUFFLE
（快步走）
She brought him back to help her buy it.
古见同学后来拉笑介回来 请他帮忙付钱
Komi!
古见同学！
-Merry Christmas! -TOO EXCITED TO WAIT INSIDE
-圣诞快乐！ -（由于等不及 站在家门口）
And…
还有…
Happy birthday!
生日快乐！
Huh? Isn't your birthday on the 25th?
怪了？古见同学 25号不是你的生日吗？
It's a day early, but as a surprise…
虽然提早一天 但我们想给你惊喜…
-Huh? -Hey, Tadano!
-怪了？ -喂 只野！
Not her birthday?
你记错她的生日了吗？
How dare…
太过分了吧…
It can't be a mistake! Maybe…
不可能搞错吧 大概啦…
IT IS TOMORROW. THANK YOU.
（明天是我生日 谢谢大家）
Oh, yeah, of course.
没错吧？
-Oh good! -RELIEF
-太好了！ -（松口气）
Okay.
好
Anyway, this is for you!
那么这个送给你！
It's a birthday present from everyone!
是大家送你的生日礼物！
Happy birthday and thanks for having us!
生日快乐 打扰了！
Happy Birthday, Komi.
生日快乐 古见同学！
H-Happy birthday!
生日快乐！
-Thanks for having us. -Happy birthday!
-打扰了！ -生日快乐！
I'm finally going to be inside Komi!
我终于要踏进古见同学家了！
Uh… Congratulations.
祝你生日快乐
She doesn't seem very happy…
她好像不是很开心
Extreme social anxiety
所谓的“交流障碍症”的人
can mean when surprised,
面对惊喜时
it's hard to know what sort of face to make.
都会不知道该流露出什么样的表情
Times like this, I wish I could say something reassuring.
真希望我能在这种时候 对她说些贴心的话
"I think you can just smile." Or something?
譬如说“你只要微笑就好”
Um… How about sending everyone a thank you email afterwards?
派对结束后 传感谢讯息给大家吧
Typical Tadano response.
很有只野同学风格的回答
Yes.
好
Christmas Party.
圣诞派对
It may seem cheery at first.
乍看之下很华丽
Look closer and it's all greed and strategy.
其实是充满欲望与谋略的聚会！
Everyone was thinking:
大家都这么思索…
W-Where should I sit so I can be next to Komi?
我要挑哪个位置坐 古见同学才会坐在我旁边？
-Augh. -Oh no.
-什么？ -天啊
I'm gonna sit on the balance ball!
我要坐在健身球上！
-Some have no greed. -Can we just sit wherever?
-当然有些人是无欲无求的 -可以随便坐吗？
But the greedy ones.
然而那群充满欲望的人
The greedier they are, the more their greed
正因为心中有欲望 而且欲望太过强烈
stops them from being able to decide where to sit!
没办法决定自己要坐在哪个位置！
Naturally, they look to Komi for a sign.
他们自然会观察古见同学的动向
SIMULATION
（想象）
Komi sits in a random spot.
古见同学随便找个位置坐下
Be the first to slide into the spot beside her.
他们要赶在古见同学坐下时 及时冲到她身旁的位置
It's highly competitive, but the chance of sitting nearby is also high!
虽然竞争率高 但能坐在她旁边的机率也很高！
It's the least risky method.
这是风险最低的手段
They all know this. They know it, however!
大家都清楚这一点 可是…
If Komi sits beside someone who's already sitting…
如果古见同学选择坐在 已入座的同学身边就没机会了
That signifies a high degree of Komi's affection.
代表古见同学对那些人很有好感
The sense of defeat will be dreadful!
会让其他人陷入庞大挫败感中！
They are living within that risk!
这群人现在面临这样的风险！
Aren't they going to sit?
都不坐下吗？
And then Komi.
然后对古见同学来说…
Her first Christmas party with friends.
这是她和朋友首次举办圣诞派对
She's never had so many friends over.
第一次有这么多朋友拜访她家
Uncharted territory.
这是未知的领域
Thus…
因此…
Her mind has gone completely blank.
她现在彻底失去思考能力
Shoko!
硝子！
Could you carry the snacks and drinks?
你可以帮我拿零食和饮料吗？
Here, Komi exits the scene.
此时古见同学暂时离场
I'll help you!
我来帮你！
I'll help, too!
我也要帮忙！
All at once, the rock-paper-scissors begins.
大家仿佛早就说好似的 开始猜拳
Leave a spot around the table empty,
他们在暖炉桌留下一个空位
and guide Komi there.
企图把古见同学诱导到这个位置
They're deciding that seating now.
他们要靠猜拳决定座位
This strategy was communicated in a single glance of solidarity.
区区一个眼神 就让他们理解彼此计划的团结力
United in friendship!
他们的友谊相当深厚！
Wow, I did it!
太好了！
I did it!
我做到了！
C'mon over, Komi.
来吧 古见同学
Here I am! Komi!
我在这里喔 古见同学！
RESERVED FOR KOMI
（为古见同学保留的座位）
There's nowhere for me to sit.
看来我没地方坐
Oh, thank you, Tadano.
谢啦 只野
I'll just sit on the floor here.
我就随意坐地板吧
I'll sit on Tadano's lap!
那我要坐在只野同学的膝盖上！
Hey, now what?
大家要玩什么？
Wanna play Swamp Bros?
我们来玩《明星大乱斗》吧
Hey, are we gonna have a toast?
对了 大家要干杯吗？
-Oh, I get it! -Hang on. I don't have juice.
-对喔！ -等一下 我没有饮料！
She was just too bashful to take the seat of honor.
她只是不好意思坐在上座吧
Can you hear me?
大家在听我说话吗？
RUMBLE
（隆隆声）
He felt her eyes boring into him for the whole party.
据说派对时他一直感受到刺人的视线
Anybody want a juice refill?
谁还要喝饮料？
I'm already pretty full.
我好饱喔
-Whose is this? -I'll have the rest!
-这是谁的？ -剩下的都归我！
Well now!
开始吧！
Who's the king?
谁是国王？
What is the King Game?
所谓的“国王游戏”
Each stick either has "king" or a number.
就是抽选写着“国王” 和其他数字的免洗筷
The king says a number and issues an order.
抽到“国王”的人 可以对抽到数字的人下命令
Often played at matchmaking parties, it's an evil game of greed and strategy.
这个暗黑游戏充斥着欲望与计谋 经常出现在联谊等场合
Here! Here!
来！
Yamai suddenly started the game.
-山井同学突然开始这个游戏 -谁是国王？
I'm the king!
我是国王！
Hasn't she been holding that one all along?
怪了？她好像原本就拿着那筷子
Alright. I'm the king just like I planned.
很好 我按照计划成为国王了！
-I paid off the ninja for Komi's number. -SIGNALS BY COUGHING
-雇用的忍者告诉我古见同学的数字 -（咳嗽次数为数字）
So what perverted order shall I give Komi?
那我要命令古见同学 做什么色色的事呢？
Wait!
等一下！
Should I exchange email addresses with her?
也可以请古见同学 跟我交换电子邮件吧
Of course I've gotten it from a secret source.
虽然我已经偷偷得知了她的电子邮件
But it's not the same!
但这是两码子事！
It's important that she asks me for mine!
重点在于亲自问古见同学再交换！
That's proof that we're good friends!
这样才能证明我们的感情很要好！
I haven't been able to ask until now, so it's a good opportunity.
我以前不好意思问她 但现在是个好机会
But I also want to make her do something perverted!
但是我也想命令她做色色的事！
Me and number three.
我要跟三号
Addresses…
交换…
Exch-ch-ch-ch…
电…
A-Are you okay?
你没事吧？
Who's the king?
谁是国王？
-Me! -So loud!
-是我！ -吵死了
Me and number four dress as Santa! I brought the costume!
四号跟国王打扮成圣诞老人 我把衣服带来了！
A new type?
太崭新了吧！
YAAAAAY
（欢呼）
The highlight of the party.
是今天气氛最热烈的时刻
Who's the king?
谁是国王？
Okay, how about number seven massages the king's shoulders?
那么请七号帮国王按摩一下肩膀
How about that?
怎么样？
Your shoulders are quite stiff, Tadano.
你的肩膀很僵硬耶 只野同学
Yeah, I guess.
是啊
Boring.
真无聊
The lowlight of the party.
是今天气氛最低迷的时刻
Who's the king?
谁是国王？
Okay, what's your order?
那你下命令吧
Hmm. Let me see…
我想想喔…
TWO MINUTES PASS.
（两分钟后）
It's hard to decide…
真的让人烦恼呢
FIVE MINUTES PASS.
（五分钟后）
What should I do?
我该下什么命令好呢？
In the end, it took ten minutes.
最后她想了整整十分钟
Who's the king?
谁是国王？
GRIN
（窃笑）
Just say something.
你说点什么吧
-MAKERU FAN CLUB MEMBER 3 -Makeru will definitely try to compete!
-（真华留粉丝团三号会员） -真华留同学绝对会想找人决胜负！
HEAVY BREATHING
（气喘吁吁）
How will she manage to lose today?
她究竟会怎么输给对方呢？
The Makeru Fan Club has strange taste.
真华留粉丝团的人想法异于常人
Numbers one through thirteen.
1号到13号
Yes, everyone.
也就是每一个人
Say to me, "I lost."
都对我说“我输了”
So that's how it's gonna be!
原来还有这招啊！
Who's the king?
谁是国王？
Oh! I-I-It's me!
天啊！是我！
Uh, um, n-n…
那么2…
Number two treats the king like a dog!
2号把国王当狗对待！
The opposite?
反而要这么做？
Who's the king?
谁是国王？
You called?
有人呼唤了我吗？
-Your numbers. -Yamai, what number are you?
-你这家伙的号码… -山井 你几号？
-I can see them in the ornaments. -Not telling!
-在圣诞装饰的反射下看得一清二楚 -我才不跟你说！
Ren Yamai!
山井恋！
So careless.
你太大意了
I'll sink you in a sea of shame.
我要让你沉没在羞耻的汪洋中
I-It can't be!
不会吧！
Marsault Les Primavera's orders.
玛路斯特蕾丝普利玛贝拉下令
Number six. Spin around three times before the king and bark like a dog!
6号 在国王面前 转三圈学狗叫一声！
Too bad, Nakanaka!
真遗憾 中中同学！
What?
什么？
She held her stick upside down!
她竟然刻意反射出 免洗筷上颠倒的号码！
-I've been deceived by this woman! -COLORED CONTACTS
-这个女人算计了我？ -（彩色隐形眼镜）
NUMBER 6
（6号）
What's this…
这算什么啊？
Who's the king?
国王是谁？
Me!
是我！
Since when?
她什么时候出现的？
I've joined in! Can I make an order?
我也一起玩了 可以下命令吗？
Uh, sure.
可以啊
Number four and nine kiss.
4号亲9号
She went straight for the jugular!
她直接明确下了最痛苦的命令！
-Uh… um… -Kiss.
-那个… -亲下去
NUMBER FOUR
（4号）
Number nine… Who's number nine?
9号 9号是谁？
Here.
是我
Shinobino.
忍野同学
Kiss! Kiss! Kiss!
亲下去！
A-Alright, on the cheek.
那我亲在脸颊上
H-Hurry up.
快一点！
BLUSH
（脸红）
Why are you turning red?!
你干吗脸红啊？
Who's the king?
国王是谁？
Huh? Hm?
什么？奇怪
Huh?
怪了
Hey!
喂！
Who is it? The king!
国王到底是谁啊？
Hm? There's really no one?
怪了？真的没人抽到国王吗？
Huh? No, it can't be. Nobody?
不会吧 不可能 没人抽到吗？
Komi!
古见同学！
W-What's her order?
她要下什么命令？
Y-Your order?
你要下什么命令？
PLEASE KEEP BEING MY FRIEND.
（请大家继续当我的朋友）
So heartwarming!
好温馨喔！
Of course!
当然啦！
The most touching moment of the day.
是今天最温馨的时刻
And after that.
后来…
Komi was in agony remembering her embarrassing order.
回想起那个命令 太过害羞 感到苦闷的古见同学
Rewind the clock to noon on December 24.
让我们倒转时间 回到12月24号的中午
Let's do something together over winter break!
我们在寒假也一起玩吧
I said it.
虽然我这么说
But it's so hard to invite her out.
但好难开口约她出去
It might have just been, you know.
她可能没有那个意思
She was just being polite.
只是客套地答应我
She probably doesn't want to hang out.
其实没有那么想跟我出去玩
-Whoa. Komi's birthday is on Christmas. -SHOKO KOMI, BIRTHDAY DECEMBER 25
-原来古见同学的生日是圣诞节啊 -（古见硝子 生日12月25日）
Huh? What day was it today?
等等 今天是几号？
THE 24TH.
（24日）
So, tomorrow is…
明天呢？
THE 25TH.
（25日）
Najimi!
驯染！
Hey!
哈啰！
Tadano, I contacted Komi and brought everyone along.
只野同学 我联络过古见同学 也带大家来了
Oh, thank you Najimi.
这样啊 谢啦 驯染
I just can't get ahold of Yamai.
但是只有山井的手机打不通
Even though it's Komi's birthday.
明天就是古见同学的生日耶
That's odd.
还真奇怪
Oh well, let's get going!
这也没办法 我们先出发吧
Yeah! Let's go! What should we do? I can't wait.
-好 走吧！ -我们要做什么呢？
-She's already here. -This won't suit Komi.
-她已经在这里了 -这不适合古见同学
Oh!
天啊！
-Wow, Yamai, you're here! -ALREADY KNEW IT WAS KOMI'S BIRTHDAY
-什么嘛 山井 你在这里啊 -（提早知道古见生日 打算偷跑）
Ren Yamai, secured.
逮到山井恋
Alright! Now we have everyone.
很好！这样大家都到齐了
Let's get started.
那我们开始
The Present Death Game.
礼物死亡游戏吧
Huh?
什么？
The rules are simple!
规则很简单
The one who chooses the present Komi likes best is the winner!
谁挑到最让古见同学 开心的礼物就能获胜！
The budget is 5,000 yen!
预算最多5000日元！
-Isn't that a little high? -Ready? Go!
-偏高呢 -准备好了吗？出发！
RECOMMENDED! HIGHLY POPULAR
（推荐！ 超受欢迎）
-Time's up! -Yay!
-时间到！ -好耶！
Let's see what you got!
公开结果吧！
Who's first?
谁要先开始？
I'll go.
从我开始
YAMAI'S CHOICE
（山井挑选的）
I've known about Komi's birthday since before summer.
我在夏天前就知道古见同学的生日
Ever since then,
从那时候开始
all I've been thinking about is Komi's present.
我无时无刻都在思考 要送给古见同学的礼物
A handmade cake.
亲手做的蛋糕
A sculpture of Komi.
古见同学的雕像
Sexy undies.
性感内衣
I thought of many things.
我思索了很多选择
But none of them were perfect.
但是总觉得都不够完美
None of them are any good!
全都是些不太好的东西
In the long darkness, a beam of light.
在漫长的黑暗中 我看到一道曙光
The thing I really want to give Komi.
我真的想送给古见同学的东西
A heartfelt present.
充满我的心意的礼物
The answer is, "me!"
那就是我自己！
-Komi, take all of me! -PRICE: PRICELESS
-古见同学 收下我的一切吧！ -（价格 无价）
Can you not go there?
请别在一开始就出现这么吓人的礼物
It's a digital society! She needs digital cash!
在这个网络社会 她需要电子货币！
That's not a present for girls.
这不是该送给女生的礼物吧
You should be one to talk!
只有你没资格说我！
Here's mine.
这是我挑的礼物
Umeboshi?
梅干？
They're tasty, never go bad, and you can eat them every day!
好吃又不会坏 每天都能吃
Hmm.
这样啊
Here's mine.
这是我挑的礼物
I need her to build up her body so we can compete any time.
她必须练好身体 随时准备好决斗
This is truly, "sending protein to your enemy," right?
这就是所谓的“雪中送高蛋白粉”
It doesn't even sound wise.
并没有说得很妙
Here's mine!
这是我挑的礼物！
-She'll never be hungry again! -2KG OF ICE CREAM
-够她吃一辈子了！ -（两公斤的香草冰淇淋）
-Stop recommending two kilo things. -ICE CREAM COMES IN LITERS.
-别推荐两公斤的东西了 -（香草冰淇淋）
I-I chose…
这是我挑的礼物…
-T-This book! -HOW TO TRAIN YOUR DOG
-就是这本书！ -（《训练狗的正确方法》）
Too much raw desire on display.
你对心中的欲望真是毫不掩饰
I chose…
我挑的是…
this!
这个东西！
-Oh, those things you see in gift shops! -OIL TIMERS, 3 FOR 4,480 YEN
-是礼品店常见的不知名商品 -（油滴沙漏 三个4480圆）
These are so fun!
这真的很有趣喔！
When I'm watching them, before I know it the day is over.
只要一直盯着看 不知为何一天很快就过去了
Why this?
你为什么想送这种东西啊？
ONIGASHIMA, KISHI, SHINOBINO, SONODA, CHIARAI'S CHOICE
（鬼岛、岸、忍野、园田 地洗井挑选的）
-I couldn't think of anything. -NOTHING
-我们想不到要送什么！ -（无）
I totally know how you feel.
我能理解你们的感受
What?
什么啊？
I expected this, so I have a second selection!
我早就预料到了 驯染二度登场！
Najimi's choice is this!
请看驯染的第二个选择！
-DANCING SANTA FOR 3,780 YEN -HO HO HO
（会跳舞的圣诞老人娃娃 3780圆 大笑）
Nobody wants that.
谁要这种东西啊？
What?
为什么不想要？
You're picky about other's presents.
不要挑剔别人送的礼物
If you're complaining so much, you'd better have something great!
只野同学 既然你意见这么多 你应该挑了好礼物吧？
-TADANO'S CHOICE -I don't know if it's great…
-（只野挑选的） -我不知道这个礼物好不好…
-Here. -160CM CAT PLUSH TOY
-就是这个 -（160厘米的猫玩偶）
Wow!
真棒！
It's huge! It's cute!
好大只喔 真可爱！
Your pick is surprisingly good!
只野同学 没想到你还挺会挑的嘛
-Surprisingly?
“没想到”是多余的
-But look at the price. -Yeah, it's pretty expensive.
-可是价钱… -没错 这还蛮贵的
So I thought we could all buy it together?
不如把它当作大家送给 古见同学的礼物 怎么样？
Oh, um. You know.
没有啦 该怎么说呢？
5,000 yen per person is a little too much.
每个人都出五千日元未免太多了
Komi would feel uncomfortable.
古见同学也会感到很有压力吧
We're buying Christmas presents too.
除了生日礼物之外 大家还会买圣诞礼物
I thought it would be just right.
我认为大家一起送这个礼物刚刚好
How about it?
怎么样？
Boring.
真无聊
-Sure, I guess it's alright? -Yeah.
-算了 这样也可以吧 -也对
I think the cat's cute!
这只猫好可爱！
Alright, let's get the cat!
好 就决定是这只猫了！
Yay!
太好了！
Wait.
等一下
If I get inside, I could legally…
如果我进到那只玩偶里面 就能合法地跟古见同学…
Wow, I'm too smart for my own good.
讨厌 我真是天才！
Komi!
古见同学！
Merry Christmas!
圣诞快乐！
And…
还有…
Happy Birthday!
生日快乐！
-Uh. -Huh?
-什么？ -怪了
She's…
难道说这是…
Hey, Tadano! Did we screw up her birthday?
喂 只野！你记错她的生日了吗？
How dare…
太过分了吧…
-Surely not… -It's a day early, but as a surprise…
-应该没搞错啊 -25号不是你的生日吗？
Yamai?
山井同学？
I-It can't be a mistake! Maybe…
不可能搞错吧 大概啦…
IT IS TOMORROW. THANK YOU.
（明天是我生日 谢谢大家）
Oh, yeah, of course.
没错吧？
RELIEF
（松口气）
Anyway, this is for you!
好 那么这个送给你！
-How's she going to react? -It's a birthday present from everyone!
-古见同学有什么反应呢？ -是大家送你的生日礼物！生日快乐
Thanks for having us!
打扰了！
Happy birthday! Thanks for having us!
生日快乐 打扰了！
Happy birthday, Komi.
生日快乐 古见同学！
-Hm? -Not very…
-怪了 -她好像不太…
Her reaction…
她的反应…
It's not great.
好冷淡
Thanks for having us! Bye!
-打扰了！ -再见！
-Bye-bye! -See you later!
-下次见！
GLOOM
（情绪低落）
It's like a funeral.
气氛跟办葬礼时没两样
Komi…
古见同学…
She didn't seem very happy about the surprise.
她看到我们准备的惊喜 好像不是很开心
Yeah.
就是说啊
-Whose is that? -Oh, I think it's me.
-谁的手机在震动？ -大概是我的
Sorry, it's me.
抱歉 是我的
Huh? Me too.
怪了 我的也是
Everyone?
大家都一样吗？
-THANK YOU FOR CELEBRATING MY BIRTHDAY. -When a person has extreme social anxiety…
所谓的“交流障碍症” 是指不擅长和人交流的一种症状
They struggle to communicate with others.
或是指有这种症状的人
It's very Komi.
真有古见同学的风格
Bear in mind.
不过需要注意的是…
They only struggle to form connections.
这些人只是不擅长社交
It doesn't mean they don't want to.
但并不表示他们不想和别人有往来
Let's do this again next year, Tadano!
我们明年也帮她庆生吧！只野同学
Yeah.
好
They all saved the email.
每个人都把它设为受保护的邮件
BONUS SCENE
（片尾彩蛋）
Thank you for your purchase.
谢谢您的购买
Is this for home use?
这是您自己留着用的吗？
HOME… USE?
（“自己留着用？”）
It's a gift.
这是要送人的
-Yes, sir. -If Shosuke wants to speak, he can.
-我知道了 -笑介想说话时可以与人正常交谈
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻译：吴敬美